A Guide to the State Records Film Collection, 1948 - 1986
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
A Guide to the State Records Film Collection, 1948-1986
The Library of Virginia
43563
58 16mm reels
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
For preservation purposes, patrons may not view the original film. Arrangements can be made to create a viewing copy upon request. Costs associated with the transfer of any film titles lacking an access copy will be borne by the patron.
Acquisition Information
In-house transfer
Historical Information
Films were originally part of a Library of Virginia circulating collection created to supply public libraries, schools, and the general public with educational film resources
Scope and Content
The collection consists of motion picture films created for K-12 classroom education and for documentary purposes. Films include works produced by the Virginia Department of Education as well as variety of state and national production companies. Highlights include a promotional film documenting the opening the Wise County Public Library and the Virginia Bicentennial Commission production of "The Past is Prologue." Some of the films have been digitized and are available on the Library of Virginia's YouTube channel. Click here to access these films: State Government Records Collection, or see links below to specific films.
Contents List
- Films, 1948-1986.
  - And You May Find It Virginia. 1977. (Folder Film)
    Colony Productions.
    28 min.
  - Behold Virginia. 1965. (Folder Film)
    Commonwealth Films, Inc.
    27 min.
  - Blue Ridge Parkway. 1968. (Folder Film)
    Walter J. Klein, Ltd.
    30 min.
  - Booker T. Washington, The Life and the Legacy 1981. (Folder Film)
    United States National Audiovisual Center.
  - Books and People n.d. (Folder Film)
    14 min.
  - Character of Lee 1962. (Folder Film)
    Documentary examining the life of General Robert E. Lee and his contributions to the Civil War and restoration efforts.
    Virginia Department of Education Film Production Service.
    Click here to access the film: Character of Lee
    16 min.
  - Charlie's Fame n.d. (Folder Film)
    MGM.
  - Chesapeake Borne Part I 1986. (Folder Film)
    National Geographic Society.
    59 min.
  - Chesapeake Borne Part II 1986. (Folder Film)
  - Chesapeake Horizons 1983. (Folder Film)
    Documentary exploring the environmental problems of the Chesapeake Bay and the impact of these problems on the livelihoods of area residents and recreational users.
    Chesapeake Bay Foundation.
    Click here to access the film: Chesapeake Horizons
  - Chesapeake - The Twilight Estuary n.d. (Folder Film)
  - Clara Barton 1978. (Folder Film)
    Handel Film Corp.
    25 min.
  - The Common Heritage - Tennessee, n.d. (Folder Film)
    20 min.
  - Common Wealth of Women, 1984. (Folder Film)
    Documentary examining the roles of women in Virginia and their contributions to Virginia Society. Includes historical review and contemporary interviews.
    Rudisill, Inc.
    Click here to access the film: Common Wealth of Women
    43 min.
  - Conway Thompson, Sculptor From Dry Bridge, 1976. (Folder Film)
    Charlotte Schrader.
  - Eye of Thomas Jefferson 1977. (Folder Film)
    Guggenheim Productions, Inc.
  - George Mason 1965. (Folder Film)
    I.Q. Films.
    48 min.
  - George Washington Birthplace - A Childhood Place 1975. (Folder Film)
    13 min.
  - George Washington's Mount Vernon 1973. (Folder Film)
    Mount Vernon Ladies Association.
  - Grant and Lee on the Civil War 1977. (Folder Film)
    Barr Films, Pasadena.
    33 min.
  - Hiking the Appalachian Trail 1975. (Folder Film)
    Walter J. Klein Co., Ltd.
  - Historic Garden Week in Virginia n.d. (Folder Film)
  - Holton Years, 1974. (Folder Film)
    Documentary examining the administration of Virginia Governor Linwood Holton.
    Click here to access the film: Holton Years
    29 min.
  - James Monroe - The Man and the Doctrine 1972. (Folder Film)
  - Jamestown 1975. (Folder Film)
  - Jamestown, A Place of Beginnings 1958. (Folder Film)
    Documentary examining the history of Jamestown from its beginnings in 1607 as the first permanent English settlement in America through its 90 years of prominence. Include dramatization of events.
    Click here to access the film: Jamestown, A Place of Beginnings
    21 min.
  - Jefferson of Monticello. 1948. (Folder Film)
    Dramatization of the life and contributions of Thomas Jefferson as seen through Jefferon's eyes as he recalls events and visits historical landmarks.
    Click here to access the film: Jefferson of Monticello
    18 min.
  - Jefferson's Monticello 1969. (Folder Film)
    Films Incorporated.
  - John Marshall 1965. (Folder Film)
  - Last Chance 1979. (Folder Film)
    Bullfrog Films, Inc.
  - Lee, the Virginian 1962. (Folder Film)
    McGraw-Hill Films.
  - Making Books n.d. (Folder Film)
    Encyclopaedia Britannica Films.
    11 min.
  - Manassas to Appomattox 1965. (Folder Film)
    Documentary exploring the role of Virginia in the Civil War.
    Click here to access the film: Manassas to Appomattox
  - Mount Vernon in Virginia 1950. (Folder Film)
    22 min.
  - Mr. Jefferson's Legacy 1976. (Folder Film)
  - Oaksie n.d. (Folder Film)
  - On the Road Virginia n.d. (Folder Film)
  - Opportunity Unlimited n.d. (Folder Film)
  - Parkway Promise n.d. (Folder Film)
    Mirage Productions.
  - Pony Penning on Chincoteague, 1955. (Folder Film)
    Documentary about the Chincoteague Pony Penning Day, which began in 1924 when the Chincoteague Volunteer Fire Company first rounded up ponies on Assateague Island to auction off in order to raise money for fire equipment.
    Click here to access the film: Pony Penning on Chincoteague
    24 min.
  - Resolve of Patrick Henry 1956. (Folder Film)
  - Richmond Remembers 200 Years 1980. (Folder Film)
    Documentary highlighting 200 years of Richmond, Virginia, history. Includes dramatizations and is narrated by Earl Hamner.
    United Virginia Bank.
    Click here to access the film: Richmond Remembers 200 Years film
  - Stonewall Jackson's Way n.d.. (Folder Film)
  - Surrender At Appomattox (Part 2) 1972. (Folder Film)
    52 min.
  - These States 1 - The New England States 1975. (Folder Film)
    Macmillan Films, Inc.
  - These States 2 - The Middle Atlantic States 1975. (Folder Film)
  - These States 3 - The Southern States 1975. (Folder Film)
  - Tom Savage - Boy of Early Virginia 1958. (Folder Film)
    Encyclopedia Britannica Corp.
  - True Story of the Civil War 1956. (Folder Film)
  - U.S. Grant - I Remember Appomattox 1976. (Folder Film)
    Coronet Films.
    17 min.
  - United States Geography - The Upper South n.d. (Folder Film)
    26 min.
  - Victory at Yorktown 1975. (Folder Film)
  - Virginia - The Pursuit of Happiness 1975. (Folder Film)
    Presented in Commemoration of Our Nation's Bicentennial to the Commonwealth of Virginia by First and Merchants Corporation, April 28 1975
  - Virginia's Flying Colors n.d. (Folder Film)
    Documentary taking a look at the many species of birds that make Virginia their home.
    Virginia Commission of Game and Inland Fisheries.
    Click here to access the film: Virginia's Flying Colors
  - Virginia's General Assembly 1980. (Folder Film)
    Documentary examining the history and functions of the Virginia General Assembly. Narrated by Speaker of the House John Warren Cooke.
    Click here to access the film: Virginia's General Assembly
  - Virginia: The Past As Prologue 1973. (Folder Film)
    Virginia Independence Bicentennial Commission.
  - Wise County Public Library 1960. (Folder Film)
    The Libary of Virginia.
    10 min.
  - Wolf Trap 1975. (Folder Film)
  - Yorktown 1983. (Folder Film)
    Phoenix Films, Inc.